Guide to the CITYarts Inc. Records 1969-2016 MS 3096
New-York Historical Society
CITYarts Inc. records
1969-2016
New-York Historical Society
CITYarts Inc. (New York, N.Y.)
Cityarts Workshop, Inc. (New York, NY)
MS 3096
63 Linear feet in 61 boxes of various sizes + 5 flat file folders
The collection includes records from CITYarts Inc. and its predecessor organization Cityarts Workshop. CITYarts is a nonprofit public arts and education organization that engages youth with professional artists in the creation of public art, including murals and mosaics. The collection is especially rich in its photographic documentation of CITYarts and Cityarts Workshop projects from 1969 into the 2010s. There is much original artwork in the collection, including drawings from youth around the world as part of the Pieces for Peace project. Program administration files include those related to publicity, press coverage, and fundraising, among others.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 6 series:
Series I. Project Binders, 1969-2016
Series II. Pieces for Peace Project, 2004-2016
Series III. General Program Administration Files, 1970s-2016
Series IV. Audiovisual (RESTRICTED), 1974-2009
Series V. Artwork, Miscellaneous Photographs, and Other Visual Materials, 1970s-2011
Series VI. Leslie Bender Artworks (RESTRICTED), circa 1981
Biographical / Historical
As stated on its website, CITYarts is a nonprofit public arts and education organization that engages youth with professional artists in the creation of public art, including murals and mosaics. The history of the organization traces back to 1968 and the formation of a community arts program under the leadership of Susan Shapiro-Kiok by the New York City Parks, Recreation, and Cultural Affairs Administration. By 1971, the program had spun off to become Cityarts Workshop, which incorporated in 1974 as a non-profit. Cityarts Workshop sought to both directly help community groups produce art, particularly murals, that reflected the community's culture and wishes, and to act as an educational resource generally for communities wanting to produce their own murals. Based in lower Manhattan, Cityarts Workshop initially focused its efforts mostly on its surrounding communities, including the Lower East Side and Chinatown, though it did occasional work elsewhere, notably with mosaic benches at Grant's Tomb. By the late 1970s, though, projects had commonly expanded to other Manhattan neighborhoods and other New York City boroughs. A 1980 inventory lists 31 murals on the Lower East Side and 22 murals in other New York areas. By the mid-1980s, well over 100 projects had been completed across the city, with murals ranging from themes of social justice to the movie, Star Wars.
It is unclear what may have formally happened with Cityarts Workshop in 1988-89; references typically say that it closed down then. In any case, in 1989 Tsipi Ben-Haim joined, or re-founded, the organization as Executive Director and its work continued, then and now under the name CITYarts Inc. While the present organization now points to 1989 as its founding year, that is a recent change from its prior datings to 1968, which is the date used throughout the documents in the collection at hand. Also, the organization's current (2021) count of over 330 completed projects includes those done by its predecessor entity from 1968-1988. (The collection includes a comprehensive list of projects through 2016; see Series I.)
CITYarts evolved in important ways under Ben-Haim's leadership. In 1995, she restructured the organization to focus on four programmatic areas: Community Identity Mural Program, Kids for Justice Mural Program, Young Minds Build Bridges Program, and the Windows of Opportunities Program. These programs remained in place through the 2010s and are reflected in the collection. Other programs also developed in later years, including Tribute to New York and New Yorkers in response to the 9/11 terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center, and Global HeARTwarming, which builds an appreciation of nature and global warming. Within these overall programs, there are various projects. An important example of this, well-represented in the collection, is Pieces for Peace with Youth from Around the World, a project under the Young Minds Build Bridges Program. Pieces for Peace involves workshops in which youth from around the world form tile-size art works illustrating their concept of peace, selections of which are used in traveling exhibitions, an online mosaic wall, and Peace Walls, including those in Harlem, Karachi, Tel-Aviv, London, and Berlin.
(The above note was based on documents from the collection (see especially the various publicity pieces in Series III), CITYarts website, and other on-line sources.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Most of the materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Some of the material in the collection is restricted for conservation reasons (audiovisual in Series IV and artwork in Series VI). See those series for specifics.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of CITYarts Inc., 2016, with the exception of the material in Series VI. Series VI was a gift of Leslie Bender in 2021.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily includes photographic documentation of CITYarts and Cityarts Workshop projects from 1969 into the 2010s. These are mostly slides and snapshots of murals and other artworks, and of the process of creating the artworks, held in binders organized by project. There are also photographs of opening events, benefits, and other organization activities.
Original artwork also comprises a substantial part of the collection. Much of this relates to the Pieces for Peace project, with submissions from school age students from around the world. Drawings of various murals or proposed murals are in the collection. One set of drawings, donated by the artist apart from the CITYarts records but included with the collection by N-YHS, are of murals by Leslie Bender.
The collection also holds various administrative records providing further context to the visual material. These include files of publicity and press coverage, fundraising efforts, such as benefits and sponsorships, subject reference files, volunteer logistics, and the like.
The collection holds over 200 videocassettes of CITYarts' projects, events and media coverage of them. These have not been reformatted and are restricted from use.
Arts fund raising.; Arts publicity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Children and peace.; Community arts projects -- New York (State) -- New York.; Mural painting and decoration, American -- New York (State) -- New York -- 20th century.; Street art.; Photographs.; Press clippings.; Project files.; Slides (photographs).; Videocassettes.; Works of art.; Ben-Haim, Tsipi; Bender, Leslie (artist)
- Series I. Project Binders, 1969-2016; 22 Linear feet in 22 cartons
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds about 130 binders documenting about 290 of CITYarts's projects from its earliest in 1969 to those of the early 2010s. The content is primarily photographic, with slides, snapshots and, later, digital formats comprising the bulk of the series. These images document the artwork itself as well as the creation process. Many binders also include related documents, such as "fact sheets" about the project, press clippings, press releases, flyers, artist statements, etc. The first box holds a master list of projects with data about artist, location, collaborators, sponsors, etc. that is useful for an overview. The bulk of the binders relate to one or more specific projects. A small set of the binders include select photographs and other materials that cut across the projects.
  The container list below includes the titles from the binder covers. Especially for binders with multiple projects not necessarily listed in the binder cover, the notes include further identifying information taken from documents within the binder and/or from the master list in Box 1. The locations/addresses recorded here are in Manhattan unless otherwise noted.
  Almost all the binders include photographs, often in the form of slides. The container list does not repeat this fact for each binder; instead the container list indicates when photos are NOT present. Almost all the binders also have at least some identifying, publicity, or other documentation with the photographs, though this is not consistently noted in the container list.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in three sets of binders, the first two sets documenting specific projects. Of these, the first set of binders is in its original sequence, numbering 1-105, which is roughly in project/chronological order, though there are exceptions. Also material on a given project may be found in multiple binders. The second set of project-specific binders has no apparent original sequence but was arranged in chronological order by the processing archivist. The third set of the series, which holds images and other material that cuts across multiple projects, is also in its original sequence, lettered A-I. Dates shown in the container list are generally the date of the project, not necessarily the date range of all documents in the binder.
  - Master Listing of Projects, 2011, 2016 (Offsite-box 1)
    Contains list of all CITYarts projects by project number. The master list includes: project number, project title, name of overall program the project was part of (e.g., Community Identity), project type (e.g., mural, sculpture), size of artwork, year, artist(s), collaborators (i.e., institutions doing and/or hosting the artwork), location, financial sponsors, and an image. The dates of 2011 and 2016 indicate when the pages of the list had been last updated by CITYarts.
  - Binder #1. Projects 1-5, 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 1)
    All 5 of these projects were done at the Alfred E. Smith Recreation Center, 80 Catherine Street, on the Lower East Side.
    Project 1: Children's Mural, 1969
    Project 2: Halls Mural, 1969
    Project 3: Sandcast Mural, 1969
    Project 4: Anti-Drug Abuse Mural, 1969
    Project 5: Black Woman's Mural (also referred to as Black Women of America Today), 1970-71
  - Binder #2. Projects 6-14, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 1)
    Project 6: Patch Work Plaza, mosaic, 1971, Washington Square Park.
    Project 7: Multi-Ethnic Mural, 1972, Corner of Bowery and Catherine Street.
    Project 8: Arise from Oppression mural, 1972, Henry Street Settlement Playhouse, 464 Grand Street.
    Project 9: Against Domestic Colonialism mural, 1972, Curtis Park/West 46th Street Playground. (Documents only, no photos. See also the unnumbered binder in box 20 relared to the mural's restoration.)
    Project 10: Grant's Tomb mosaic bench project is not in this binder, but see binder #67.
    Project 11: History of Chinese Immigration to the U.S. (also referred to in the documents as the Asian Mural), 1972, Chatham Square.
    Project 12: 7th Precinct Youth Council mural, 1972, 8-20 Ludlow Street.
    Project 13: A Jewish Ethnic Mural, 1973, Bialystoker Home for the Aged, East Broadway.
    Project 14: Effects of Budget Cuts, 1973, Forsyth and Division Streets.
  - Binder #3. Projects 15-20, 1973-1977, 1979 (Offsite-box 1)
    Project 15: Destruction of Nature, mural, 1973, Sanitation Department Building, 140 Madison Street.
    Project 16: Chinatown Today, mural, 1973, 109 East Broadway.
    Project 17: Afro-Latin Mural, 1973, 50 Avenue C.
    Project 18: New Birth, mural, 1974, 181 Chrystie Street.
    Project 19: Art as an Alternative to Violence, mural, 1974, 73 Delancey Street.
    Project 20: Italian Mural, 1974, New York Post Building, 465 Water Street. (See also binder 4.)
    [Project 55]: Rivington Street Parking, mural, 1979, Rivington & Chrystie streets. (Items out of sequence; see also binder 13).
  - Binder #4. Projects 20-23, 1974 (Offsite-box 2)
    Project 20: Italian Mural, 1974, New York Post Building, 465 Water Street. (See also binder 3.)
    Project 21: Black Liberation Mural, 1974, Water Resources Building, South and Clinton streets.
    Project 22: Women Hold Up Half the Sky, mural, 1974, P.S. 63, 3rd Street & Avenue A. (See also binder 7.)
    Project 23: Wall of Respect for Women, mural, 1974, Lower East Side Community Manpower Service Center, 165 East Broadway. (See also binder 6.)
  - Binder #5. Project 24: Chi Lai/Arriba/Rise Up, 1974 (Offsite-box 2)
    Mural, P.S. 2 Playground, Madison and Pike streets.
  - Binder #6. Project 23: Wall of Respect for Women, 1974 (Offsite-box 2)
    Mural, Lower East Side Community Manpower Service Center, 165 East Broadway. (See also binder 4.)
  - Binder #7. Project 22: Women Hold Up Half the Sky, 1974 (Offsite-box 2)
    Related Materials
    Mural, P.S. 63, 3rd Street and Avenue A. (See also binder 4.)
  - Binder #8. Projects 25 & 26, 1975 (Offsite-box 2)
    Project 25: Seeds for Progressive Change, mural, 1975, 142 Forsyth Street.
    Project 26: Phoenix, mural, 1975, 42nd Street & 8th Avenue. (The documents for this project also refer to Project 65, Henry Street Settlement Playhouse, 1980. See binder 12.)
  - Binder #9. Projects 27 & 28, 1975 (Offsite-box 3)
    Project 27: Hospital Mural, 1975, Gouverneur Hospital, 227 Madison Street.
    Project 28: Puerto Rican Heritage Mural, 1975, Rutgers Community Center, Madison and Rutgers streets.
  - Binder #10. Projects 29-34, 1976 (Offsite-box 3)
    Project 29: Crear Una Sociedad Nueva, mural, 1976, 14 2nd Avenue.
    Project 30: Su Casa, mural, 1976, Lower East Side Service Center's Methadone-to-Abstinence Rehabilitation location, 9 Gouverneur Slip East
    Project 31: Por Los Ninos, mural, 1976, 135 Mangin Street.
    Project 32: Tribute to John Lennon, mural, 1976, 2nd Avenue & Houston Street. (Fact sheet only, no photos.)
    Project 33: Let Our People Grow, mural, 1976, J.H.S. 65, 46 Forsyth Street.
    Project 34: Douglass Street Mural, 1976, 389 Douglass Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn.
  - Binder #11. Projects 35-51, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 4)
    Project 35: Instead of a specific title or brief reference, the project fact sheet records this statement: "The Painting is about the struggles and aspirations of the community seen through the eyes of Black and Latin teenagers who designed it," 1977, 5th Avenue & 1st Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn. (Documents here include those related to controversy over the mural).
    Project 36: Building the Community, 1976, 166 West 132nd Street. (Documents only, no photos).
    Project 37: Plaza Cultural, mural, 1977, 10th Street and Avenue C. (Documents here include agreement with landlord).
    Project 38: Yesterday, Today, and Tomorrow, mural, 1978, Saint Barnabus House, 304 Mulberry Street.
    Project 39: The Performing Arts, mural, 1977, Tompkins Square Park (includes drawing).
    No Project 40 in the binder.
    Project 41: Wall of Respect for the Working People of Chinatown, mural, 1977, Canal Street between Bowery and Hester Street.
    Project 42: Tito Rodriquez Memorial Mural, 1977, East 10th Street at Avenue D. (Fact sheet only, no photos.)
    Project 43: Children are Born to be Happy, mural, 1978, the records conflict on the location, but was possibly the Sloane Children's Center, 630 East 6th Street.
    Project 44: Promenade Mural, Peace and Harmony in Nature, mural, Salvation Army, 1151 Bushwick Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 45: Sports Mural, 1978, 122nd Street and Mount Morris Park West.
    Project 46: Celebration in Central Park Mural, 1978, American Nursing Home, 26 Avenue B.
    Project 47: El Espiritu Latino, mural, 1978, 36 Wilson Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 48: Star Wars Mural, 1978, Northside Center for Child Development, 1301 5th Avenue. (Documents only, no photos.)
    Project 49: Liberty with Birds, mural, 1978, P.S. 63, East 3rd Street. (Documents only, no photos.)
    Project 50: 12th Street Garden Mural, 1978, 12th Street between Avenues A and B.
    Project 51: Stapleton Library Mural Project, 1978, Wright Street, Staten Island. (Documents only, no photos.)
  - Binder #12. Projects 62-79, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 4)
    Project 62: Lincoln Hospital Satellite Clinic mural, 1980, Bronx. (Fact sheet only, no photos.)
    Project 63: Building the Community (also referred to as Building the Community in Struggle and Unity), mural, 166 West 132nd Street.
    Project 64: Brooklyn and Our Neighborhood, mural, 1980, Fifth Avenue and 54th Street, Brooklyn. (Fact sheet only, no photos. See binder 14 for photos.)
    Project 65: Henry Street Settlement mural, 1980, Lower East Side. (Fact sheet only, no photos. See also binders 8 and 14 for photos.)
    Project 66: Lion and Tiger, mural, East 9th Street and Avenue C. (Fact sheet only, no photos)
    Project 67: Green Market mural, 1980, Manhattan. (Fact sheet only, no photos. See binder 14 for photos.)
    Project 68: Delancey Street mural, 1980, F train's Delancey Street station. (Fact sheet only, no photos.)
    Project 69: The Pot of Knowledge/Black Pride, mural, 1980, Martin de Porres Center, 3-10 Astoria Blvd., Queens. (See also binder 14.)
    Project 70: Mu-Kei/Dream Landscape, mural, 1980, Bellevue Hospital, 27th (or 30th?) Street and 1st Avenue.
    Project 71: Changes in Growth, mural, 1980, 259 Monroe Street, Passaic, NJ. (See also binder 14.)
    Project 72: Sunrise/Sol Naciente, mosaic, 1980, Roberto Clemente State Park, Cedar Avenue and West Tremont Bridge, Bronx.
    Project 73: The Renaissance of Church Ave, mural, 1980, 1711 Church Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 74: Pollination, 1980-81, mural, East 48th Street Community Garden, Brooklyn.
    Project 75: Unidos Venceremos, mural, East 103rd Street between Lexington and Park avenues. (Documents only, no photos. See the unnumbered binder for the 2012 restoration project in Box 21, which has 1980s photos.)
    Project 76: Wall of Achievement, mural, 1980, P.S. 150, Jackson Heights, Queens. (Fact sheet only, no photos.)
    Project 77: The Home, mural, 1980, 280 Stone Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 78: Dawn of Peace, Senior Citizens Mural Project, 1980, Brookdale Senior Citizens Center, 817 Avenue H, Brooklyn. (Documents only, no photos. See binder 14 for photos.)
    Project 79: Dancing Colors and Sounds, mural, 1980, P.S. 192, West 136th Street. (Documents only, no photos. See binder 14 for photos.)
  - Binder #13. Projects 52-61, 1979-1981 (Offsite-box 4)
    Project 52: The Future Springs from the Past, mural, 1979, Langston Hughes Library, Northern Boulevard, Queens.
    Project 53: God Bless Our Home, mural, 1979, 1590 East New York Avenue(?), Brooklyn.
    Project 54: The Four Seasons, mural, 1979, 48th Street and Church Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 55: Rivington Street Parking mural, 1979, Rivington and Chrystie streets. (Documents only, no photos.)
    Project 56: That's the Way of the World, mural, 1979, 2182 Atlantic Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 57: Port Authority Mural, 42nd Street and 8th Avenue.
    Project 58: Coming Home, mural, 1979, 280 Stone Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 59: Mosaic Workshop, 1979-81.
    Project 60: People on the Bench, mural, 1980, Harlem Hospital Medical Center, Lexox Avenue.
    Project 61: Rebuilding the Community in Unity and Struggle, mural, 1980, 317 Rockaway Avenue, Brooklyn.
  - Binder #14. Various Projects (64, 65, 67, 69, 71, 78, 79), 1980 (Offsite-box 5)
    Project 64: Brooklyn and our Neighborhood, Fifth Avenue and 54th Street, Brooklyn.
    Project 65: Henry Street Settlement, 1980.
    Project 67: Green Market, 1980, Manhattan.
    Project 69: The Pot of Knowledge/Black Pride, 1980, Martin de Porres Center, 3-10 Astoria Blvd., Queens.
    Project 71: Changes in Growth, 1980, 259 Monroe Street, Passaic, NJ
    Project 78: Dawn of Peace, 1980, Brookdale Senior Citizens Center, 817 Avenue H, Bronx.
    Project 79: Dancing Colors and Sounds, 1980, P.S. 192,West 136th Street.
    See binder 12 for additional documents related to these projects.
  - Binder #15. Various Projects (136, 137, 141, 146-49, 153, 155), 1987-1991, 1999 (Offsite-box 5)
    Overall, this binder primarily includes documents, with only some photos.
    Project 136: Geometric Abstractions, mural, 1987, J.H.S. 57, 125 Stuyvesant Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 137: Louis Armstrong: The Prevalence of Love, Devotion, and Jazz, mural, 1987, 107-10 Northern Blvd., Queens.
    Project 141: Muneco De Nieve (Snow Man), mural, 1988, Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic. (See also binder 25.)
    Project 146: Through the Bricks, mural, 1989, J.H.S. 51, 350 Fifth Avenue, Brooklyn. (See also binder 26.)
    Project 147: Career Quilt, mural, 1989, P.S. 86, 2756 Reservoir Avenue, Bronx.
    Project 148: Queens, mural, 1990, I.S. 126, 31-35 21st Street, Queens. (See also binder 26.)
    Project 149: P.E.P.'s Bing-Bong Circus, mural, 1990, P.S. 198, 1700 3rd Avenue.
    Project 152: Past, Present, Future, mural, Classon Avenue Garden, Brooklyn. (See also binder 26.)
    Project 153: Save the Earth (or Colors of Music?), mural, 1989-90, Joan of Arc School, 154 West 93rd Street.(See also binder 26.)
    Project 155: The Creative Process Exhibition, 1991, The Cork Gallery-Lincoln Center, Avery Fisher Hall, Bronx Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Newhouse Center for Contemporary Art.
    Kids for Justice Project, 1999.
    Also a packet an assortment of "random" documents that seem to date around 1999 concerning various projects.
  - Binder #16. Projects 80-89, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 5)
    Project 80: Reflections, mural, 1981, Brooklyn. (Documents only, no photos.)
    Project 81: Sunnyside Mural, 40-01 43rd Avenue, Queens.
    Project 82: Summercast Live on Channel 13, 1981.
    Project 83: Girls Town, mural, 1981, 307 East 12th Street.
    Project 84: Beach Street Entrance, mosaic mural, 1981, 116th Street, Rockaway Boardwalk.
    Project 85: Set Design, mural, 1981, P.S. 166, 33-09 35th Avenue, Queens.
    Project 86: Remember the Dream, mural, 1981, 4-5 Astoria Blvd., Queens.
    Project 87: Dungeons and Dragons, mural, 1981, 15-145 Mini School, 33-34 80th Street, Queens.
    Project 88: P.S. 82 Mural, 1982, 88-02 144th Street, Queens. (continues in binder 17)
    Project 89: Avenue C Mural, 1982, 73-75 Avenue C. (continues in binder 17)
  - Binder #17. Various Projects (88, 90-94, 96-98, 100), 1982 (Offsite-box 5)
    Project 88: P.S. 82 Mural, 1982, 88-02 144th Street, Queens. (See also binder 16.)
    Project 89: Avenue C Mural, 1982, 73-75 Avenue C. (See also binder 16.)
    Project 90: Flushing Mural, 1982, L.I.R.R. trestle between 40th and 41st avenues, Queens.
    Project 91: Sunset Park Mural, 1982, P.S. 169, 4305 7th Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 92: Stepping Stones, mosaic sculpture, 1982, Manhattan.
    Project 93: Hebrew Educational Society of Canarsie Mural, 1982, 9502 Seaview Avenue, Brooklyn.
    Project 94: Puerto Rico: Feasts, Landscape and Culture, mural, 1982, Borinquen Plaza Senior Citizen Center, 80 Seigel Street, Brooklyn.
    Project 96: Louis Armstrong Mural, 1982, 32-02 Junction Blvd., Queens.
    Project 97: East Harlem Mural, East 103rd Street and Park Avenue.
    Project 98: Avenue X Gravesend Mural, 1982, Citibank, 265 Avenue X, Brooklyn.
    Project 100: Learning (Hunter Elementary School Mural), 1982, 71 East 94th Street.
  - Binder #18. Projects 90-105, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 6)
    Several of these projects are also found in binder 17.
    Project 90: Flushing Mural, 1982, L.I.R.R. trestle between 40th and 41st avenues, Queens. (Documents only, no photos. See binder 17.)
    Project 91: Sunset Park Mural, 1982, P.S. 169, 4305 7th Avenue, Brooklyn. (Documents only, no photos. See binder 17.)